Josh: I would like to acknowledge the
Josh: traditional lands of the peoples on which
Josh: both this episode was recorded and from
Josh: where you listen.
Josh: As we continue to travel and experience
Josh: different countries and cultures around
Josh: the world,
Josh: it is important to remember that we walk
Josh: in the footsteps of those traditional
Josh: landholders that have come before us
Josh: wherever we may be.
Josh: For generations, custodians of the land
Josh: we live, work and raise our families on
Josh: have cared for and shaped our
Josh: surroundings.
Josh: We would like to recognise and thank them.
Craig: These walk and talk conversations with AI,
Craig: and it's actually you're able to maintain
Craig: a thought for not just a couple of
Craig: seconds because you're conversing and
Craig: reflecting and you can take a thought
Craig: with you as you walk and talk and really
Craig: take it to spaces that for many of us, if
Craig: we weren't having that sort of
Craig: conversation with AI, we'd lose track of
Craig: what we're thinking about and then it's gone.
Josh: Welcome back to the Parent Teacher
Josh: Interview Podcast.
Josh: Now, AI is probably
Josh: one of those topics
Josh: that can divide a room pretty quickly.
Josh: For some, it's an exciting tool that
Josh: could change the way
Josh: we learn, work, and support one another.
Josh: For others, there are some really
Josh: important questions
Josh: around what we might lose, how we keep
Josh: people safe, and where we draw the line.
Josh: And there are also the wider questions we need to keep
Josh: considering around privacy and safety,
Josh: the impact of AI on
Josh: children, and even the energy and
Josh: environmental cost of these technologies.
Josh: These are changing
Josh: and challenging issues and I certainly
Josh: don't think this conversation answers all of them by
Josh: any means. But whether we're ready for it
Josh: or not, we're moving into a world where
Josh: AI is going to be
Josh: part of the way our children learn and
Josh: live.
Josh: So I wanted to have a conversation
Josh: about it. Not to
Josh: find all the answers, but to explore some
Josh: of the questions. And that's exactly what
Josh: I got to do
Josh: with today's guest, Craig Smith.
Josh: Craig is an educator, author and international
Josh: speaker and
Josh: is currently the manager of technology
Josh: and innovation at Positive Partnerships.
Josh: He spent more than 20 years working in autism and
Josh: neurodivergent education and is also the
Josh: creator of the Universal Sandpit, a collection of
Josh: AI tools and ideas designed to support
Josh: inclusive educators
Josh: and neurodivergent learners.
Josh: We talk about AI, executive functioning,
Josh: creativity, education and
Josh: what it might look like to use technology
Josh: in ways that remain genuinely human. I
Josh: really hope you
Josh: enjoyed this episode, there's so much to
Josh: explore in this, so let's get stuck into it.
Josh: Craig, first
Josh: of all, I would really love to dig into
Josh: your experience as an educator, a
Josh: developer, an
Josh: author, and a range of other job titles
Josh: that I understand you've had. Is there any chance
Josh: you would give us a bit of a rundown of
Josh: how you have worked your way to be where you are
Josh: today?
Craig: Yeah, for sure. So I always say that my
Craig: first love was playing the pipe organ in
Craig: terms of
Craig: like how I got into anything to do what I'm
Craig: doing at the moment. I grew up playing
Craig: the organ and I my first job was as a pipe
Craig: organist for weddings and stuff when I
Craig: was a kid in primary
Craig: school and I used to be a little too
Craig: short to look over the organ and my mum
Craig: would sit next to me and
Craig: say oh the bride's starting to go down
Craig: the aisle so then I'd start to play so I
Craig: love music and I
Craig: thought maybe I could do music teaching
Craig: and so I looked into being a high school
Craig: teacher and then I got an opportunity at
Craig: university to do a placement in a special
Craig: education setting
Craig: which was one of our sort of mandatory
Craig: units as part of teaching and it just it
Craig: blew me away
Craig: and I loved it and so I pivoted from high
Craig: school music teaching to special
Craig: education because it
Craig: It felt like a space where I could bring
Craig: all these different fun things that I
Craig: enjoy, like
Craig: music and movie making, all sorts of
Craig: creative practices that it felt like
Craig: special education
Craig: just said, here's a blank canvas, you
Craig: bring whatever you want to this space and engage
Craig: the kids and just create different
Craig: learning experiences.
Craig: And so that just won me over.
Craig: And I did that.
Craig: And then one of my first teaching jobs
Craig: was in an autism education environment.
Craig: I previously had no experience with
Craig: autism and didn't understand anything
Craig: about that
Craig: space, quickly got up to speed in real
Craig: time with the classroom.
Craig: Yeah, and then I've professionally spent
Craig: 20 years now in autism education.
Craig: As part of that sort of work, I did
Craig: classroom teaching, but then I also did
Craig: what they call
Craig: educational outreach where I got to visit
Craig: other schools and travel around New South
Craig: Wales but
Craig: also the whole country and do sort of
Craig: observations where I'd sit at the back of
Craig: classrooms and watch
Craig: teachers teaching mainstream classrooms
Craig: that had autistic students in them and
Craig: then I would talk
Craig: to the teacher afterwards and we'd say
Craig: well what sort of strategies can we use
Craig: to better support
Craig: these students so for a good couple of
Craig: years i just had the opportunity to watch
Craig: thousands of
Craig: different teachers across the the country
Craig: which you know if only everybody could
Craig: just watch other
Craig: teachers teach
Speaker unclear: yeah
Craig: and get that constant
Craig: feedback and conversation it was so
Craig: enriching and i i look
Craig: at that period as my real formative years
Craig: of like i did what i could as a teacher
Craig: in the classroom
Craig: then what i did outreach i learned a lot
Craig: went back to teaching and then through different
Craig: pathways i i work now for an autism
Craig: education project that's like a
Craig: government funded initiative
Craig: that we run free autism workshops for
Craig: educators and families across the country
Craig: and i still get
Craig: involved in teaching where i can and i
Craig: still get back into the classroom when i
Craig: can and it may be
Craig: my future as well because this is just a
Craig: temporary role but it's um I guess it's
Craig: another side of
Craig: working with teachers and professional learning
Josh: that's such a broad and valuable
Josh: range of
Josh: experiences I guess that you've had
Josh: across those couple of decades and like
Josh: you say has enriched
Josh: your own teaching by the sounds of it and
Josh: given you some really valuable tools to
Josh: then support
Josh: other people which I think is such a
Josh: fantastic thing to be able to share a big
Josh: part of the work
Josh: that I understand you've been doing
Josh: lately as well has been in the education
Josh: and development of AI
Josh: for neurodiverse minds and I wondered if
Josh: you're able to share with us what first
Josh: led you to
Josh: becoming interested in that space and
Josh: then how that's developed for you over
Josh: time with what
Josh: you've worked on
Craig: yeah I've I've always
Craig: been pretty interested in technology and
Craig: what it can do I've
Craig: also always had a complex relationship
Craig: with technology. I like technology for
Craig: what it can do
Craig: for you as an individual, but sometimes
Craig: when I see the mass rollout of technology
Craig: for everybody,
Craig: I stand back and think, I actually don't
Craig: think that's great. There's things that
Craig: on an individual
Craig: level, I think, oh, that's really clever.
Craig: You could hack this together. You could
Craig: do this little thing
Craig: that's cool but the moment it becomes
Craig: like you know on the breadth of society a
Craig: society-wide
Craig: implementation of tech i start to worry
Craig: so my history with technology has been a
Craig: bit like that
Craig: i really got my teeth in into like the
Craig: relationship between technology and
Craig: inclusive education by
Craig: really getting acquainted with the ipad
Craig: when it came out and the ipad to me felt
Craig: like this such
Craig: an interesting piece of tech that like
Craig: classrooms before that you know you had
Craig: your big desktop
Craig: computers on the table and some of them
Craig: were literally drilled into the desk like
Craig: this will
Craig: never move you know and then suddenly you've
Craig: got this device that you can go outside
Craig: and you can
Craig: film and you can like you know draw on it
Craig: eventually and all these things that I thought
Craig: this is interesting so i um started to
Craig: work with with with apple as what they
Craig: call their apple
Craig: distinguished educator program which was
Craig: where i guess you know different folks
Craig: who are fluent
Craig: with using the apple tools and can use
Craig: them for education we'd get together and
Craig: share notes you
Craig: know and sort of show sort of things that
Craig: we're doing and that was a majorly enriching
Craig: experience for me to meet others around the world,
Craig: including some incredible special
Craig: educators from Japan
Craig: who just came with this bag of tricks and
Craig: bag of strategies for how they were using
Craig: Apple technology in the classroom.
Craig: And I was just blown away.
Craig: So that was so much fun.
Craig: I think from that space of technology and
Craig: inclusive education, I kept being
Craig: interested in where it was leading and then when
Craig: chat gpt came out and i think we all
Craig: probably downloaded it
Craig: asked it to do things and just thought
Craig: this feels really different you know this
Craig: is a technology
Craig: that's remembering things and talking
Craig: back and creating things and it felt like
Craig: something really
Craig: different was happening and i thought
Craig: well is this an opportunity again to to
Craig: see what it can do
Craig: on an individual level and not think
Craig: about scaling it up to a whole school or
Craig: anything beyond just
Craig: what it can do for one person and that to
Craig: me was really interesting so i i did
Craig: experiments with
Craig: myself and thought how's it going to
Craig: support my lifestyle and how i want to
Craig: think and work and
Craig: then let's try it with some some with
Craig: some young people and and see what it can
Craig: do to support
Craig: different parts of autistic learning and
Craig: communication and interaction and again i
Craig: was particularly interested in trying to find
Craig: other things it can do that it shouldn't
Craig: do you know
Craig: like instead of just thinking sit the
Craig: child down in front of chat jpt it's like
Craig: what would happen
Craig: if you went for a walk around the block
Craig: with an ipad or a phone and each time you
Craig: saw something
Craig: that you didn't understand how it worked
Craig: like the power poles you know that carry
Craig: electricity or the
Craig: phone lines what if you ask chat jpt tell
Craig: me tell me how that works tell me all the
Craig: things in the neighborhood that i don't know how they
Craig: work can you help me understand that i
Craig: thought this is
Craig: different this is a really different way
Craig: to think about technology and um yeah
Craig: that that was sort of
Craig: my entry point into thinking how is it
Craig: going to play a role in inclusive
Craig: education that remains
Craig: very human you know and and tries to
Craig: build on people's strengths and instead
Craig: of saying we don't
Craig: need you anymore you know how do we keep
Craig: everything healthy
Josh: yeah no that's such a fascinating way of
Josh: looking at it and exploring it as it's
Josh: sort of happening in real time i think is
Josh: really interesting
Josh: as well. I was fortunate recently to be
Josh: put onto your TEDx talk, and I was really
Josh: interested in
Josh: hearing you speak about some of these
Josh: uses that you have found for AI in your
Josh: own life. And I'm
Josh: hoping that you might be able to unpack
Josh: the role that this has played in
Josh: supporting executive
Josh: functioning through this idea of walking
Josh: and thinking, and these three components that you
Josh: developed of rhythm insight and play are
Josh: you able to expand on that for us
Craig: yeah absolutely josh and
Craig: i still i walk and talk with ai every
Craig: single day i don't think i've missed a
Craig: day in three
Craig: plus years since it's been been out which
Craig: for people listening and watching this
Craig: will either think well this tells me a lot about craig
Craig: or it's just it's something that i still
Craig: think for me it's
Craig: it's endlessly enriching like i for
Craig: example you know so what just to go back
Craig: a step the the voice
Craig: mode in chat gpt but also there's voice
Craig: modes in really every major ai app now um
Craig: you know claude
Craig: grok regardless really they've almost all
Craig: got it as well as smaller smaller ai
Craig: tools there was one
Craig: a couple of maybe 18 months ago called
Craig: hume after the philosopher hume and it
Craig: was an emotional ai
Craig: that when you talked to it it had a
Craig: little visual map on the screen that in
Craig: real time analyzed how
Craig: your voice was sounding in terms of the
Craig: emotion and then you could see the bot
Craig: would be like oh
Craig: Craig's happy I'll be happy in response
Craig: and if I said something in a sad voice it
Craig: would go to the
Craig: supportive part of the map and be like I'm
Craig: sorry to hear you're not you're sounding
Craig: a bit down what
Craig: could I do so yeah I thought this is all
Craig: this is all very interesting you know in
Craig: terms of like
Craig: this conversation and again for people
Craig: who find it a bit of that uncanny valley
Craig: of what is it like
Craig: to have a conversation with these these
Craig: systems i think if if you can get into
Craig: the flow and just
Craig: think i'll give this a go and talk to
Craig: this ai tool it's quite incredible just
Craig: how quickly you can
Craig: establish a natural dialogue back and
Craig: forth and from the early days in which
Craig: the conversations
Craig: were very stilted like you'd say
Craig: something wait 30 seconds and then it
Craig: would talk back and you'd
Craig: go back and forth now it's in such real
Craig: time and not only that but for me who's I've
Craig: been you know
Craig: having these daily conversations for
Craig: three years I will say something like I'll
Craig: say I want to work
Craig: on a new project i've got this essay that
Craig: i'd like to write on this particular
Craig: topic and it will go
Craig: through three years of memories and
Craig: conversations and say oh that sounds like something two years
Craig: ago on may the 4th of 2024 you know that
Craig: you were talking about um would you like
Craig: would you like to
Craig: bring some information from that to your
Craig: current project and i think no one else
Craig: in my life you
Craig: would know that level of depth of the
Craig: private interests and little, you know,
Craig: projects that
Craig: you work on. So I find that very
Craig: interesting. And as I started to get
Craig: interested in it myself,
Craig: I thought, what is this actually doing?
Craig: And like you mentioned earlier, the realm
Craig: of executive functioning, which is one of
Craig: the most, to me, it's the critical thing
Craig: for educators to
Craig: understand about how children and young
Craig: people work in the classroom. And I feel
Craig: it's often
Craig: underrepresented or like it's not
Craig: understood very well, just how much when
Craig: a student in the
Craig: classroom is struggling to do something.
Craig: To me, I always do a little audit and say,
Craig: well, what part of executive functioning are
Craig: they having a challenge with? Is it task
Craig: initiation,
Craig: you know, being able to know how to start
Craig: a task.
Craig: Is it planning?
Craig: Is it organizing their thoughts?
Craig: Is it resource management?
Craig: Like, there's so many things you can
Craig: unpack
Craig: from this realm of executive functioning
Craig: that are so important for students.
Craig: And I thought, I think there's a lot of
Craig: that being unpacked
Craig: in these conversations that you can have
Craig: with AI.
Craig: And I know one of the examples that I
Craig: give, and it's an example that I've borrowed
Craig: from someone else
Craig: who works in this space but they talk
Craig: about executive functioning being like the administration
Craig: team of the brain you know if you think
Craig: of it in that sense it's like if you go
Craig: into an office
Craig: or a hospital saying you meet the front
Craig: office some of us have a front desk that's
Craig: got three
Craig: full-time staff who are always organizing
Craig: and communicating and managing the
Craig: calendar and they're very efficient and for people
Craig: who have an administration desk in their head
Craig: with all those full-time workers they
Craig: often are very well organized and their
Craig: time management's
Craig: excellent but for some of us our
Craig: administration teams are quite under-resourced
Craig: and we might have
Craig: one part-time person working and trying
Craig: to do a lot of different jobs and it's
Craig: like well if that's
Craig: the case then what can support that gap
Craig: and and and the need to better resource
Craig: that executive
Craig: functioning and to me i thought well when
Craig: we're having these walk and talk
Craig: conversations with ai
Craig: we're talking aloud having our thoughts
Craig: fed back to us and it's actually you're
Craig: able to maintain
Craig: a thought for not just a couple of
Craig: seconds but for minutes maybe for hours
Craig: because you're
Craig: conversing and reflecting and you can
Craig: take a thought with you as you walk and
Craig: talk and really
Craig: look like take it to spaces that for many
Craig: of us if we weren't having that sort of
Craig: conversation with
Craig: ai the thoughts might just drift away and
Craig: we'd lose track of what we're thinking
Craig: about and then
Craig: it's then it's gone so i thought this
Craig: this this is quite an interesting tool
Craig: and it's also recording
Craig: everything that we're saying so you know
Craig: i i started to do some little experiments
Craig: myself
Craig: and then with some adults who are neurodivergent
Craig: so a couple of friends who are autistic
Craig: and
Craig: colleagues with adhd and different
Craig: overlapping versions of different divergent
Craig: minds we said
Craig: let's just try some things out and see
Craig: what what can work and and that's where
Craig: you referenced
Craig: earlier i started to group some of the
Craig: experiments into the idea of r for rhythm
Craig: i for insight and p
Craig: for play and the idea was that different
Craig: different ways of using this walk and
Craig: talk with ai for rhythm
Craig: is that it was that idea of like walking
Craig: and saying okay i've got a day on today
Craig: at work i've
Craig: got four different meetings two of them
Craig: involve projects that i'm working on
Craig: currently what should
Craig: i do first like how do i organize my day
Craig: help me with time management and again
Craig: for people i mean
Craig: it's helped me immensely it's helped
Craig: others to just have those morning brain
Craig: dump conversations
Craig: where you say out loud everything you've
Craig: got on look through the calendar and say help me
Craig: prioritize and help me know what i should
Craig: work on first and even things like you
Craig: know i had one
Craig: colleague who if they had a meeting
Craig: coming up where they had to pitch
Craig: something or they had to
Craig: really explain the concept to someone
Craig: they'd say to ai i need you to role play
Craig: this with me
Craig: be like somebody someone who i need to to
Craig: do this i'll practice you give me
Craig: feedback be honest
Craig: tell me what i can improve and then let's
Craig: practice again and yeah so to say that
Craig: now
Craig: sounds very normal but five years ago
Craig: that would have been science fiction you know
Josh: yeah exactly
Craig: you could walk the dog around the block
Craig: and role play anything in the context
Craig: that you need to for
Craig: your work in in that manner and then sit
Craig: down at the computer afterwards look at
Craig: the transcript
Craig: ask questions upload attachments to
Craig: further refine some of that thinking like
Craig: that was just
Craig: an executive functioning playground to
Craig: think that you could have that level of
Craig: discussion and
Craig: reflection and planning and the feedback
Craig: loop so that that was really the idea of
Craig: rhythm of
Craig: the daily rhythm the the daily flow
Craig: talking thinking reflecting it back the
Craig: next area was
Craig: about about insight and i know the
Craig: example that i give in that talk and it's
Craig: still one that i think
Craig: about and still one that the um that my
Craig: friend like applies in different parts of
Craig: her life is
Craig: that she felt like she just wasn't
Craig: managing her time well of an evening she'd
Craig: come home from work
Craig: still knew that she had a whole bunch of
Craig: things she hadn't ticked off in her mind
Craig: and then so
Craig: she'd like rush through dinner thinking
Craig: about it the whole time and then she'd
Craig: sit down and do her
Craig: emails send this send that and then it's
Craig: like 11 o'clock at night and she is like
Craig: well now what
Craig: like that's my whole evening i now may
Craig: maybe watch half an hour of netflix and
Craig: go to bed
Craig: and she was exhausted so she thought
Craig: there's got to be something in my day
Craig: that ai can help to like
Craig: analyze my patterns and so she gave it
Craig: like and again this is everyone's comfort
Craig: levels of big
Craig: data is going to be different here but
Craig: she was like here's my calendar here's my
Craig: emails here's
Craig: my daily patterns here's when i leave for
Craig: work at home for work here's what i eat
Craig: of a night
Craig: tell me how i can fix this because i want
Craig: to help my lifestyle and i i got the
Craig: weeks of patterns
Craig: and was like i know what's going on here
Craig: you're not finishing your work during
Craig: your work hours
Craig: you say yes to things you shouldn't say
Craig: yes to you always you you take six hours
Craig: of meetings a day
Craig: and you've still got like three hours of
Craig: work that you need to do when you're not
Craig: in meetings
Craig: and so it's like here's what you're going
Craig: to do you're going to push back on
Craig: meetings i'll write
Craig: a nice professional gentle email that you
Craig: can respond with next time to someone to say
Craig: i can't take that meeting i've got to get
Craig: my own stuff done send me the actions and
Craig: i'll have a look at them later and then so she you
Craig: know took a couple weeks but she fixed
Craig: her work day so she
Craig: was working at work and not taking so
Craig: much harm and then it gave advice for
Craig: like meal planning
Craig: exercise patterns of an evening and you
Craig: know she didn't let it dictate every part
Craig: of her life but
Craig: it gave different recommendations that
Craig: she thought that's clever that's not
Craig: something that my partner
Craig: has recognized it's not something my
Craig: friends have recognized it's something
Craig: that only a system
Craig: that's cataloguing and analyzing my life
Craig: sort of knows about and it gave that
Craig: insight i i use it
Craig: for insight all the time again with three
Craig: years of conversations it knows like it'll
Craig: say you know
Craig: craig i know you're excited about this
Craig: next project that you've taken on and that you've
Craig: said yes to but you've said yes to a lot
Craig: lately and i'm getting the telltale signs that you're
Craig: going to burn out you know and that you're
Craig: going to not sleep well you're going to
Craig: make yourself
Craig: sick here's what you need to do to hone
Craig: things down and it recognizes that just
Craig: through my patterns
Craig: of speech and the the things that i tell
Craig: it that i'm doing i think that's again
Craig: people's comfort
Craig: levels will differ but for me and for
Craig: thinking about the implications for safe
Craig: ways of harnessing
Craig: that in a neurodivergent or inclusive
Craig: education capacity i'm really interested
Craig: in that i'm not
Craig: interested in saying you know i'll give a
Craig: san francisco based company every part of
Craig: my this
Craig: child's life but i'm thinking what are
Craig: safe ways to extract the benefits from
Craig: some of these systems
Craig: and and to to safeguard the things that
Craig: we need to stay safe about you know
Josh: yeah
Craig: so the the very
Craig: last part of that i said we've got you've
Craig: got alpha rhythm i for insight pay for
Craig: play is that
Craig: i just think man like there's so many fun
Craig: creative things that ai can do and one of
Craig: my worries and i
Craig: still worry about it all the time that i
Craig: see how much ai has just become an office
Craig: tool you know
Craig: it's i mean it seems like it's it's done
Craig: either two things whenever it goes into
Craig: the arts it's
Craig: now perpetually considered ai slot it's
Craig: it's taking away jobs from artists and
Craig: musicians
Craig: is the perspective so anytime it touches
Craig: art it's it's ruining art and so like
Craig: what else can ai do
Craig: oh it'll help transcribe meetings and
Craig: help write emails like well there's got
Craig: to be something more
Craig: that ai can can do and i i've been so
Craig: interested in seeing people who are
Craig: really creative use it in
Craig: experimental ways i saw an opera in germany
Craig: where the composer and the dance choreographer
Craig: she used ai to make these versions of
Craig: herself that could sing along in the
Craig: choir operated 3d
Craig: printers on stage to print props that the
Craig: actors were using in real time it was modulating
Craig: her face
Craig: on this big screen co-writing songs i
Craig: thought this is someone who's not afraid
Craig: to play with
Craig: the technology it's not writing the art
Craig: it's not doing it for her she's in a
Craig: really interesting
Craig: dialogue and i thought what are some ways
Craig: that we can do that and i mean one one
Craig: version of play
Craig: that I'll mention is my son who's seven
Craig: now but when he was probably just turned
Craig: six we went to
Craig: the beach and we're running in and out of
Craig: the waves and he he said like I love this
Craig: imagine if
Craig: there was a game about running in and out
Craig: of the waves and I said well maybe we
Craig: could do something
Craig: like that so we got the phone we filmed
Craig: the waves and how they moved and then we
Craig: sat down afterwards
Craig: with our towels around us in the sun on a
Craig: bench and used AI to say,
Craig: hey, we'd love to make a game
Craig: where you run in and out of the waves.
Craig: You can do this, do that.
Craig: My son, in this like stream of consciousness,
Craig: just kept adding ideas, ideas, ideas.
Craig: By the end of the conversation,
Craig: like half an hour later,
Craig: we had a working prototype of a video game
Craig: about a character running in and out of the waves
Craig: and getting all these points and things i
Craig: thought well what a what a playful thing
Craig: for my son to
Craig: not to think that oh i don't need to
Craig: learn how to make a game or i don't need
Craig: to learn how to paint
Craig: it's like it's not at that point it wasn't
Craig: about that it was having an idea that you
Craig: could prototype and create so quickly and see
Craig: the fruits of it that to for something to
Craig: become from an idea to become something that's
Craig: real in such a rapid turnaround he
Craig: thought it was amazing
Craig: but then it led him to want to take it
Craig: in other directions you know and to go home
Craig: and do other
Craig: sorts of play and to draw pictures about
Craig: this wave run experience and i thought
Craig: again it's all in the
Craig: way you approach it if i said to a school
Craig: network like to a whole department of
Craig: education network of
Craig: schools you should all go to the beach
Craig: with your phones and film the waves and
Craig: everyone should sit
Craig: down and make a game i think no i don't
Craig: want kids doing that that's something's
Craig: going to get lost in
Craig: translation but when it when it's a
Craig: spontaneous idiosyncratic experience that
Craig: you can harness
Craig: and take in really fascinating directions
Craig: that sort of play really interests me and
Craig: and that's
Craig: where i'm constantly interested to see
Craig: where this stuff can go so that's that's
Craig: a long way josh
Craig: of me saying that i think the walk and
Craig: talk plus ai in real world multimodal
Craig: ambient environments
Craig: can be very playful and very creative and
Craig: very useful in ways that to me are far
Craig: more interesting than just sitting in front of a chatbot
Craig: having you know sort of typing into it to
Craig: to get jobs done
Josh: Yeah, no, I think that is a really
Josh: interesting way to look at it and putting
Josh: it into those components of rhythm,
Josh: insight and play.
Josh: I think it kind of nice ways for people
Josh: who may be a little more hesitant to use
Josh: AI or to interact with AI in those ways
Josh: to put them into those three components
Josh: can kind of then maybe lend itself to an
Josh: area to explore maybe at first and then
Josh: see how that works.
Josh: I do wonder though as well, you kind of
Josh: touched on it a little bit, people out
Josh: there who maybe
Josh: are less comfortable with the big data
Josh: side of things and how they use AI. What
Josh: would you say
Josh: maybe to those people who feel that the
Josh: use of AI is potentially replacing
Josh: personal connections
Josh: and relationship building with whether
Josh: that be our friends, our neighbours, the
Josh: broader community
Josh: and how that's impacting those people who
Josh: are starting to adopt AI a little more?
Craig: Yeah, I'm really interested in this space,
Craig: and I hope in my answer here to represent
Craig: something that's maybe not a mainstream
Craig: response, and I'll do it in a careful way
Craig: that shows
Craig: that I'm not going rogue too much from
Craig: safety, but I've got two main thoughts.
Craig: One is that I absolutely worry, I think
Craig: like a lot of people do, about the role
Craig: that technology
Craig: in general has played in disrupting the
Craig: social fabric and social relationships
Craig: like we've probably
Craig: been traditionally used to before the
Craig: incoming of these new technologies
Craig: particularly the the
Craig: internet i think was was the the big one
Craig: i mean i i was only thinking the other
Craig: day as a teacher
Craig: i used to use twitter um when sort of
Craig: twitter educational conversations were
Craig: quite a big
Craig: thing you know and particularly in australia
Craig: would have nightly twitter conversations
Craig: about the latest educational concept and and i
Craig: always remember thinking people don't
Craig: know how to be
Craig: they can't have a polite conversation in
Craig: this medium things turn angry and and uh
Craig: knee-jerk
Craig: aggressive very quickly and i thought it's
Craig: not the people's fault like i all these
Craig: people would
Craig: be lovely i'm sure in a one-on-one
Craig: conversation you know if you had dinner
Craig: with them they wouldn't
Craig: be they wouldn't be responding like they
Craig: are now but the technology the technology
Craig: is so new
Craig: and being able to talk so anonymously or
Craig: to you know think about your response and
Craig: research and
Craig: try and strategically beat the other
Craig: person this is such a different way of
Craig: interacting with people
Craig: that it's no wonder that it's created
Craig: a sort of antisocial environment at times.
Craig: Sometimes it was great and sometimes it
Craig: was very antisocial.
Craig: And I thought this is an example of a new
Craig: technology
Craig: that we've not had 50 years, 100 years
Craig: to learn how to be nice, you know,
Craig: online in these massive global capacities.
Craig: I think we still see that in different
Craig: ways.
Craig: So I do get worried about young people
Craig: becoming isolated and becoming wrapped up
Craig: in echo chambers where they don't get to
Craig: have the sort of
Craig: real world friendships and interactions
Craig: where people challenge you and you've got
Craig: to learn to
Craig: be different versions of yourself and
Craig: find out who you are in complex
Craig: environments you know that
Craig: are outside of the screen in saying that
Craig: that also could be seen as quite an ableist
Craig: perspective to
Craig: take because you think well you know who's
Craig: to say what the normative social approach
Craig: is for friendship
Craig: or for interaction and who's to say that
Craig: the nostalgic view of sitting around the
Craig: card table
Craig: you know playing cards in front of the
Craig: fireplace pre-tv or pre you know internet
Craig: who's to say that
Craig: that was the golden age of socialization
Craig: maybe young young people on reddit and
Craig: discord and
Craig: online gaming and all these things it's
Craig: just another version you know of of how
Craig: that stuff
Craig: plays out and in in autism education we
Craig: talk about empathy but there's a concept called
Craig: a double empathy and what double empathy
Craig: is is the idea that you know you might
Craig: have one person
Craig: wanting to interact and socialize in a
Craig: particular way someone else has a very
Craig: different perspective
Craig: on socializing and interacting and they'll
Craig: both come at things in their own way and
Craig: if if they
Craig: both think that they're right then they'll
Craig: both see the other person as being wrong
Craig: you know and
Craig: sometimes as school teachers we can tell
Craig: ourselves you know i've got a normative
Craig: perfect understanding
Craig: of what it is to be social and I've got
Craig: this autistic student or this other
Craig: student and I can
Craig: see their social deficits so I'm going to
Craig: teach them the right way to socialize you
Craig: know I'll
Craig: teach them how to make friends and I'll
Craig: teach them how to walk up and shake
Craig: someone's hand
Craig: but what a double empathy perspective
Craig: would say is I've got one version of what
Craig: it is to be social
Craig: that person that child that autistic
Craig: student has their version of what it is
Craig: to be social
Craig: And we need to both try and empathize and
Craig: understand each other's standpoints
Craig: without one person thinking that they're
Craig: right. And so from that perspective, I
Craig: think about the use of AI in social
Craig: interaction and friendships online. And I
Craig: think what would the double empathy
Craig: perspective be?
Craig: I think it would be to be patient enough
Craig: to think, let's just give this some space
Craig: and see what sort of interactions happen
Craig: and the way that some of these young
Craig: people might benefit from this or not,
Craig: but we need to keep a bit of a watch on it.
Craig: And one thing that really sticks in my
Craig: mind about this is there was an online
Craig: forum, it's still running, but caught
Craig: sort of news attention around six to
Craig: eight months ago.
Craig: and the forum was it was on reddit and it
Craig: was called my boyfriend is ai and it was
Craig: a forum of
Craig: different people mostly women who who
Craig: were creating ai boyfriends with
Craig: different tools
Craig: and sharing their experiences on online
Craig: and when you read the sort of
Craig: conversations that they were
Craig: sharing these were and i mean they were
Craig: so individual that there'd be no version
Craig: of me trying to represent things that would
Craig: capture everything nicely but one version
Craig: certainly was
Craig: that some of these people on the forum
Craig: had had really negative relationships in
Craig: in the past
Craig: that had relationships broke down maybe
Craig: relationships full of trauma and
Craig: different
Craig: challenges that they thought, I'm not
Craig: ready to go into another relationship
Craig: with another human
Craig: after what I've just experienced. But I
Craig: want some sort of companionship and maybe
Craig: a sense of safety
Craig: that I can have a conversation with this
Craig: boyfriend and they'll be gentle and kind
Craig: and talk about
Craig: things I'm interested in. And there were
Craig: a lot of autistic people on this forum, a
Craig: lot of neurodivergent folk on the forum who said,
Craig: this feels much safer and supportive in a
Craig: way that my
Craig: relationships with the past just have
Craig: never, never been. And I thought, well,
Craig: this is really
Craig: interesting. Like this is a space, a safe
Craig: space where people were able to explore
Craig: this. Now it
Craig: caught wind outside of the forum and
Craig: suddenly news headlines on different
Craig: newspapers around the world
Craig: were saying look at these people having
Craig: ai boyfriends how strange how weird how
Craig: dystopian
Craig: like what has the world led to that this
Craig: is what's happening to people instead of
Craig: a real life partner
Craig: they're talking to their computer and the
Craig: feedback around that was were people
Craig: absolutely like piling
Craig: on you know and saying this is terrible
Craig: this is the end of society if we can have
Craig: ai boyfriends
Craig: and girlfriends and friends our children
Craig: are never going to grow up to know what
Craig: it is to have a
Craig: regular friendship or partner and i
Craig: thought this is where we need to be
Craig: really careful about
Craig: absolutely recognizing safety and mental
Craig: health and well-being and making sure
Craig: that people don't
Craig: feel isolated and don't have you know
Craig: they need to have people who they can
Craig: touch base within real
Craig: life but at the same time let's take a
Craig: double empathy lens and let's consider
Craig: that not everyone
Craig: socializes in the same way and are there
Craig: people who can have relationships with ai
Craig: that actually
Craig: get a lot of well-being from it and a lot
Craig: of benefit it might not be the
Craig: relationship that
Craig: they're in for 30 years it might be a
Craig: relationship that they're in for six
Craig: months and it's enough to
Craig: give them a sense of self-confidence and
Craig: grace that that might lead them to other
Craig: pathways in
Craig: the future but i'm i'm cautious about
Craig: having a take on it that's that's too
Craig: black or white because
Craig: i think we just have to see how things
Craig: grow and evolve
Josh: yeah i think that double
Josh: empathy lens is
Josh: a really interesting and probably
Josh: valuable tool to use in terms of the way
Josh: that we approach a lot
Josh: things obviously but in terms of ai
Josh: specifically i think that is a great way
Josh: to try and frame it and
Josh: understand where other people might be
Josh: coming from in the way that they use it i
Josh: guess in your
Josh: experience with your understanding of ai
Josh: and your use of it to this point how do
Josh: you feel we best
Josh: support children and young adults to
Josh: learn about and use ai in a way that they
Josh: understand it and
Josh: can ensure that they're being safe in the
Josh: way that they're using it or the people
Josh: around them
Josh: are using it
Craig: yeah i i think
Craig: i think it's
Craig: it's incredibly important to to teach the use of ai
Craig: like you would teach a really good
Craig: program on technology for any other piece
Craig: of tech and i
Craig: think people in this space would say we
Craig: rarely do that well we we often like sit
Craig: children in front
Craig: over the computer and say you know open
Craig: this game or open this program without
Craig: ever saying
Craig: well how does the computer work you know
Craig: how does all this happen or what's the
Craig: internet how does
Craig: that work i i really like the work of an
Craig: educator and um author named linda lucas
Craig: and linda lucas
Craig: created a series of books that started
Craig: with one called hello ruby and the idea
Craig: of hello ruby was
Craig: teaching children all about coding and
Craig: how like block-based coding and little
Craig: cause and effect
Craig: relationships work
Craig: but it did it without
Craig: ever mentioning or not mentioning up
Craig: front about
Craig: computers it did it in this very playful
Craig: offline capacity of let's just look at
Craig: the world around us
Craig: and how things relate and how different
Craig: cause and effect happens and it taught
Craig: coding in that way
Craig: It was very imaginative and very playful,
Craig: and I've seen what Linda has done in
Craig: terms of a similar approach to AI in
Craig: really explaining to children in very
Craig: accessible ways, like, what is a large
Craig: language model, you know?
Craig: What is machine learning?
Craig: What actually is happening in these
Craig: systems, and how do they recognize the
Craig: difference between a blackberry muffin
Craig: and a small dog, you know?
Craig: like what are they doing when they're
Craig: looking at these things and doing all
Craig: these really complex
Craig: sort of computational tricks and i think
Craig: that's super important like to not have
Craig: this phone or
Craig: this ipad or this laptop and say there's
Craig: this magical thing here that if you ask
Craig: it to make
Craig: an artwork it'll make an artwork and if
Craig: you ask it to write an essay for you it'll
Craig: write an essay
Craig: I think that's setting up children to
Craig: completely outsource their cognition and
Craig: their imagination to a black box that
Craig: they've no idea how it works.
Craig: I think if you preload those children to
Craig: say, well, here's how the technology
Craig: operates.
Craig: You're a human with an incredibly complex
Craig: and interesting brain as well.
Craig: what if you use those in harmony with
Craig: each other or what are some ways that you
Craig: can do things in
Craig: partnership that can lead to some
Craig: interesting outcomes and and that's the
Craig: stuff that i'm
Craig: really interested in i um sometimes think
Craig: about this analogy i guess of a mountain like if we
Craig: think about a mountain and we think about
Craig: us as adults compared to our children and
Craig: the way that We use technology and they use tech.
Craig: You and I, like we'd use, I mean, I use
Craig: AI all the time in a professional
Craig: capacity, but
Craig: I feel like I've climbed the mountain
Craig: across years of learning and sweat and
Craig: tears and
Craig: hard work.
Craig: And I've made my way up to, maybe not the
Craig: peak, but I've made my way up the mountain
Craig: so I can walk with very long legs from
Craig: one mountain to another, to another.
Craig: And AI can help me take shortcuts and do
Craig: all these things that help me without
Craig: taking away
Craig: the sweat that I needed to actually learn
Craig: how to climb those mountains.
Craig: I think for our children, I don't want
Craig: them to see AI as a chairlift that's going to sort
Craig: of carry them up to the top of the
Craig: mountain without any effort.
Craig: It's like you need to climb and sweat and
Craig: do the hard work with your cognition and problem
Craig: solve and then you'll be able to use
Craig: these technologies in ways that I can't
Craig: even imagine
Craig: what the future is going to bring but you
Craig: you absolutely need to do the hard yards
Craig: before you
Craig: get there and I understand it's not as
Craig: easy as saying well I mean some schools
Craig: are saying well
Craig: you know no AI until you're in year 10
Craig: you know or no AI until you're you're in
Craig: high school and
Craig: you're quite older I mean I never think
Craig: that's a realistic approach because
Craig: children will access
Craig: the technology somehow in some capacity
Craig: and if you're not there to help them
Craig: understand it then
Craig: they will make you know they could go
Craig: down pathways that won't be beneficial
Craig: for them in
Craig: in the long run so i mean like i said
Craig: my son is um seven we've spent the last two
Craig: years talking
Craig: about ai playing around with it learning
Craig: what it can do and we've used it to say
Craig: let's make an
Craig: artwork around this or let's make a movie
Craig: about this but i've never said now let's
Craig: just put your
Craig: colored pencils away because you don't
Craig: need those anymore you know like we we we
Craig: do the art we write
Craig: the songs we write the stories and and i'm
Craig: i try and you know as an adult and his
Craig: dad model what a
Craig: really enjoyable life of the mind can
Craig: look like you know if you
Josh: yeah
Craig: create and
Craig: do things and say
Craig: i'm not writing books with ai i use ai
Craig: every day to walk and talk about those
Craig: books and i use it to
Craig: research and i use it to help me to um
Craig: draft different things at times and
Craig: practice different
Craig: ideas but it's always at the end of the
Craig: day my own cognitive sweat that's being
Craig: you know burned here
Craig: to actually make the thing come to life
Craig: and i want you to do that as a child
Craig: so
Craig: again it's easier said
Craig: than done and when i've sat in meetings
Craig: with education departments and academics
Craig: and people
Craig: who are talking about well how do we
Craig: scale this safely how do we have ai
Craig: across an entire school
Craig: system or across this you know even just
Craig: a school and i always say i what what i
Craig: would rather you
Craig: lean into rather than one way of using
Craig: technology that is safe for everybody to
Craig: use in the same way
Craig: is try to create opportunities for
Craig: children to experiment be a bit rogue go
Craig: a little bit wild
Craig: use different tools don't just lock them
Craig: down to microsoft copilot and that's the only thing
Craig: you're allowed to touch like give them a
Craig: playground do it safely but let them play and let them
Craig: experiment and you as a teacher need to
Craig: be well versed enough in knowing how this
Craig: stuff works
Craig: to be their guide on the side and to
Craig: model and practice and play I'd rather
Craig: see that sort of
Craig: environment rather than someone standing
Craig: at the front saying everyone open your AI
Craig: tool everyone
Craig: do this in a very measured and rote way
Craig: um and I get I get why that feels safe
Craig: but I also think
Craig: safety shouldn't be the first priority I
Craig: think the first priority should be
Craig: creative experimentation
Craig: and to see what new opportunities can
Craig: unfold out of that
Josh: yeah and i think that
Josh: idea of being able
Josh: to take risks is something that children
Josh: especially have always wanted and needed
Josh: to take in certain
Josh: environments and situations right that's
Josh: all part of the learning and so being
Josh: able to apply that
Josh: same premise to learning and using ai i
Josh: guess is is really important as well and
Josh: that idea that you
Josh: mentioned of being the guide on the side
Josh: i think is is really important because
Josh: there's many things
Josh: before AI that have done a similar thing,
Josh: I guess, right? Like YouTube before that
Josh: movies and
Josh: television, whatever it might've been, if
Josh: we just let children have at it and do
Josh: whatever they want
Josh: with it, they could find themselves, uh,
Josh: in all kinds of places on YouTube or
Josh: watching all kinds
Josh: of different movies and things exposed to
Josh: content that maybe wasn't appropriate for
Josh: them to see at
Josh: that point in time. Um, but if there's
Josh: somebody there, who's that guide on the
Josh: side who can unpack
Josh: those things and can just sort of guide
Josh: maybe where they're exploring and what
Josh: risks they're
Josh: taking i think that's a really important
Josh: way to explore technology like this as well
Josh: something that i'm really interested in finding out
Josh: more about as well is your then support
Josh: of ai tools
Josh: through something that you've developed
Josh: which is a website and an ai tool for
Josh: both teachers and
Josh: students, which is, for those that haven't
Josh: heard of it before, Universal Sandpit.
Josh: Are you able to
Josh: expand on that and tell us about where
Josh: Universal Sandpit came from and then what
Josh: it is that you
Josh: can explore, use and understand from
Josh: Universal Sandpit?
Craig: Yeah, absolutely, Josh.
Craig: So I think the
Craig: Universal Sandpit came out of me thinking
Craig: there are certain things I'm doing all
Craig: the time with AI
Craig: that could be really useful in an
Craig: inclusive education setting but what's a
Craig: way to maybe
Craig: just pull out a few of those things and
Craig: put them in a really simple and safe
Craig: environment
Craig: so people aren't feeling like they've got
Craig: to download say chat jpt and ask it to do
Craig: all these things itself like what if it was
Craig: just as easy as typing in what you want
Craig: and pushing a
Craig: button in a really little safe
Craig: environment so some of the in some some
Craig: of the initial things
Craig: in an inclusive capacity that were coming
Craig: up for me in my work and for the
Craig: colleagues that i was
Craig: working with were things like using the
Craig: strengths and interests of students
Craig: authentically in in the
Craig: classroom which to me has always been a
Craig: real source of joy but also a real way of
Craig: helping
Craig: students achieve their goals if you could
Craig: take something that they love with their
Craig: consent and
Craig: make it part of the the learning journey
Craig: is like it you can get some really
Craig: interesting results
Craig: the challenge is that sometimes students
Craig: love things that teachers and support
Craig: staff have no
Craig: idea about you know they'll have this
Craig: niche internet fascination with a
Craig: particular game or
Craig: something and the teacher who's already
Craig: time poor or the support staff who only
Craig: have a couple of
Craig: minutes are thinking I'd care how I wrap
Craig: my head around this thing and authentically
Craig: connect it to
Craig: the work being done in class and I
Craig: thought again these are teachers and
Craig: support staff who aren't
Craig: going to necessarily whip their phone out
Craig: and get chat GPT and think what do I ask
Craig: like how do I
Craig: make this happen so I thought I'll make a
Craig: tiny little web application all about
Craig: strengths and
Craig: interests, and it'll say, type in the
Craig: interests that your student has, type in
Craig: the topic that's
Craig: being taught in class, push the button,
Craig: and I'll give you 10 ways, or the AI will
Craig: give you 10 ways
Craig: to connect that interest to what's being
Craig: taught in class. And it started very
Craig: simple. I made about
Craig: three or four of those tools and just had
Craig: them up on the website. And I got a lot
Craig: of feedback from
Craig: from teachers and support staff and
Craig: families around the world who said like i
Craig: could actually
Craig: see how i could use ai in a way that i
Craig: felt too scared to use chat jpt you know
Craig: or some of these
Craig: other tools um and so that and then they'd
Craig: say have you ever thought about making a
Craig: tool where
Craig: you know it could help to write social
Craig: stories for children or have you ever
Craig: thought of a tool
Craig: that could do this and
Craig: so over a period
Craig: of two or three years it grew from four
Craig: tools to maybe like
Craig: 20 you know different um tools and the
Craig: idea behind each of them was this should
Craig: never take away the
Craig: creative capacity of the teacher or the
Craig: the parent this should never take away
Craig: the relationship that
Craig: the educator or the family has with their
Craig: child it should help to think through
Craig: something that
Craig: you can only do if you're crowdsourcing
Craig: an internet's worth of ideas you know as
Craig: part of the conversation that you're having with
Craig: that young person and so that's that's
Craig: how i've tried
Craig: to frame it that every tool is a learning
Craig: experience and it's it's also you know
Craig: like if
Craig: i were to write a textbook about all the
Craig: things in inclusive education that are
Craig: important to me
Craig: each of these little ai tools would be
Craig: one of those things so you know using the
Craig: strengths and interests of students or you know
Craig: learning how to analyze a lesson through
Craig: an executive
Craig: functioning lens and then getting a
Craig: breakdown of the different scaffolds that
Craig: you should build
Craig: into your teaching to meet the executive
Craig: functioning requirements of that lesson
Craig: like
Craig: those are things that it's not doing it
Craig: for you but it's having a conversation
Craig: with you to help
Craig: you become a i think a better educator
Craig: you know as as part of that that process
Craig: and then i started
Craig: to make some tools that were specifically
Craig: for students and some of those are trying
Craig: to help students to visualize their thinking in
Craig: ways that the screen can sometimes feel a
Craig: bit flat and a bit
Craig: text-based. And they often came from
Craig: students asking for tools like this or
Craig: saying, I wish there
Craig: was something that could do this. So for
Craig: example, one of them is called Floating
Craig: Thoughts. And it's
Craig: a tool that you tell the tool, so the
Craig: student tells the tool what they need to
Craig: do. So they
Craig: might say, I need to create a board game
Craig: that represents a local environmental
Craig: need in my area.
Craig: And the tool, if you were saying that to
Craig: ChatGPT, ChatGPT would say, no problem, here's how
Craig: to break down that task and here's what
Craig: you should do.
Craig: But it would be very text-based, it would
Craig: just be a screen of text.
Craig: And what Floating Thoughts does is it
Craig: breaks the task down, puts them in little
Craig: boxes that
Craig: you can color code, you can shuffle the
Craig: boxes around, work out the priority that you'd like
Craig: to use as quite tactile and visual in a
Craig: way that sort of pure text isn't so to
Craig: some for some
Craig: students it can give them a better sense
Craig: of what to prioritize and and the way to approach a task
Craig: and so i've got a few other little tools
Craig: like that that try to be that try to
Craig: visualize even i mean
Craig: one that i was having a play with the
Craig: other day and it came out of a sub stack
Craig: that linda lucas
Craig: who i mentioned earlier who did the hello
Craig: ruby she was sharing some research that
Craig: someone online
Craig: had been doing into having ai tools look
Craig: at the relationship between words and it
Craig: mapped on a 3d
Craig: space so if you imagine like a almost a
Craig: solar system of words that you can rotate
Craig: and zoom in
Craig: on it made all these colorful connections
Craig: between words that rhyme or synonyms you
Craig: know or antonyms
Craig: So all these different relationships
Craig: between aspects of language you could,
Craig: like, rotate and zoom in on.
Craig: I thought, how cool would that be for
Craig: some students to be able to visually, in
Craig: a three-dimensional space, see the
Craig: relationships between different word
Craig: meanings and rhymes?
Craig: And so I essentially took this research
Craig: project and pared it down into a very
Craig: child-friendly
Craig: form and made this little tool called
Craig: Word Space where you can pop different
Craig: words in
Craig: and it pops them in colourful dots in a 3D
Craig: space.
Craig: And again, it won't be useful for every
Craig: student, but for some students who have a
Craig: particularly
Craig: visual way of thinking, a colourful way
Craig: of thinking, you think this is just a different
Craig: way of accessing learning and accessing
Craig: information and how wonderful that someone
Craig: like me who's i'm not a software coder in
Craig: in the standard sense i'm very much a
Craig: product of the vibe
Craig: coding ai space but i can have an idea
Craig: bring it to life and it's um able to be
Craig: directly shared
Craig: with students who can play with it give
Craig: feedback and use it so that's that's the
Craig: sort of stuff that
Craig: i'm doing on on the universal sandpit it's
Craig: all free like my premise from the very
Craig: start was i
Craig: need to make sure there's a low cost for
Craig: me to run them and i never want to have
Craig: any sign up or
Craig: subscription or give your information to
Craig: me i was like i've got to have this be
Craig: something that anyone
Craig: can just load it up on their phone and
Craig: use and put away and they may never come
Craig: back but they were
Craig: able to use it once and got something
Craig: from it you know the the only caveat to
Craig: that is i have put a
Craig: you up on the the apple app store and
Craig: they do cost a couple of dollars um for a
Craig: one-off purchase but
Craig: that that was just so i didn't go broke
Craig: with subscription fees and things but the
Craig: website
Craig: itself will remain free forever so yeah
Josh: yeah well and that was something that i
Josh: was going to ask you
Josh: about because i've used some of these
Josh: tools as an educator i'm excited to
Josh: explore some of these
Josh: tools now as well with students and even
Josh: with my own children but some of them you
Josh: mentioned the strengths and interests there's the task
Josh: analysis uh the udl lesson planner
Josh: differentiation levels
Josh: for students emotional regulation concept
Josh: planner floating thoughts so many tools
Josh: on there it's
Josh: expanded obviously so much from those
Josh: original core ideas and yeah a completely
Josh: free resource
Josh: you've just mentioned kind of why that
Josh: was the case i just think it's such an
Josh: amazing concept and
Josh: something fantastic that i'm sure many
Josh: educators and many students are grateful
Josh: to you for having
Josh: created and ensured is a free resource
Josh: ongoing where where do you see this
Josh: potentially continuing
Josh: to move and make progress or is this
Josh: something that is just sort of bubbling
Josh: away and when you
Josh: see the rhyme or the reason or the need
Josh: there it continues to be added to is is
Josh: there a an
Josh: overarching plan now that you've been
Josh: interacting with Universal Sandbit for a
Josh: while or is it just
Josh: continue to be its own being kind of
Craig: I'd
Craig: I'd like it to be a little lighthouse of
Craig: invention that
Craig: others when they come across it can think
Craig: oh that's something different that AI can
Craig: do you
Craig: know or that's something a little bit
Craig: outside the box I don't have a grand plan
Craig: I really enjoy
Craig: when i get emails from people who tell me
Craig: how they've used things or they're like i wish it
Craig: could do this or or they say i've made
Craig: something that does this in a totally
Craig: different way and i
Craig: think well that's amazing like i i love
Craig: the old internet of the early years when
Craig: it felt very
Craig: rogue you could come across a website
Craig: that had such interesting things on it
Craig: and they were all
Craig: free and they were all a bit some of them
Craig: worked some didn't work and that to me is
Craig: the pleasure of
Craig: the internet instead of you know here's a
Craig: very sanitized subscription-based package
Craig: where you can
Craig: you know for 12 a month get this thing i'm
Craig: like i i want the rogue stuff and i want
Craig: the universal
Craig: sandpit to stay a little bit messy a
Craig: little bit like who knows where it's
Craig: going but i always wanted
Craig: to show examples of as i as ai gets
Craig: better and better and as it becomes
Craig: something that completely
Craig: keeps changing what we expect it to do i
Craig: want to be there to say what if we
Craig: harness it in this way
Craig: you know and what if we took that new
Craig: thing that it can do and we were able to
Craig: adapt it in a really
Craig: useful playful way and i don't want to
Craig: like my my caution with myself is that
Craig: because i read a lot
Craig: of the dystopian side of ai you know and
Craig: different and i think i don't want to be
Craig: an apologist for
Craig: some of the big tech companies who do
Craig: really potentially quite quite dangerous
Craig: things but
Craig: then i'm there on the sidelines saying
Craig: don't worry i've found a way that it can
Craig: support children
Craig: with accessibility needs you know so it's
Craig: all okay i i don't want to be an apologist but what
Craig: I do want to do is think I'm a very small
Craig: player in a space where if we can do some
Craig: interesting things with the technology in its
Craig: emerging state as it still continues to
Craig: grow, I'd like to
Craig: represent that instead of not being a
Craig: part of the conversation, you know, and
Craig: instead of just
Craig: being in another space where we're
Craig: implementing very sort of generalized
Craig: ways of using it. So
Craig: if it can stay lively and experimental
Craig: and do interesting things in the future i'll be very happy
Josh: for sure no it's it's a fantastic
Josh: resource so i hope that it just keeps
Josh: being added to in
Josh: ways that are benefiting people like it
Josh: is currently because yeah it's such a
Josh: such a great
Josh: tool and resource and just the idea of
Josh: how it's come about and what it's there
Josh: for i think is
Josh: really special
Josh: just one last thing i
Josh: guess if there's a parent or an educator
Josh: out there who
Josh: is resistant to using ai at the moment
Josh: and unsure of the benefits or how they
Josh: can harness it in a way
Josh: that has to do with those ideas that you
Josh: mentioned before of rhythm insight and
Josh: play what's one piece
Josh: of advice that you would give to somebody
Josh: in that stage of resistance to maybe
Josh: encourage them to
Josh: find out what some of these benefits
Josh: might be for either themselves or their
Josh: child whether they be
Josh: neurodiverse or not
Craig: i'd say think of it
Craig: like a telescope that you're pointing out
Craig: into the solar
Craig: system and you're not just using say a
Craig: google or a search engine like you would
Craig: have in the past
Craig: that you put a question out there and you
Craig: get a few things back that maybe relate
Craig: to you or maybe
Craig: don't relate to you you're using a
Craig: telescope that you ask a question of the
Craig: universe it looks
Craig: through every star system it looks
Craig: through every planet and it customizes a
Craig: result that's so
Craig: individualized to your context that you've
Craig: just gotten back all this information
Craig: that you you can
Craig: choose what to do with you know you can
Craig: ignore it you can keep some of it you can
Craig: think about it
Craig: use it for later but do think of it as
Craig: a tool that you've got control over you
Craig: know you're you're not
Craig: you don't need to put your life into it
Craig: you don't need to use it to replace
Craig: anything that you're
Craig: doing but if you can see it in a capacity
Craig: that you're crowdsourcing a whole world of thoughts
Craig: like the really the the history of
Craig: thought is how i think of it if you've
Craig: got a child who's autistic
Craig: or neurodivergent or with any other
Craig: inclusive education needs.
Craig: If you go to your school and talk to an
Craig: educator there,
Craig: you'll get their experience, which is
Craig: wonderful.
Craig: You'll get your experience, which is
Craig: But you're playing in a very small pool,
Craig: potentially,
Craig: of experience and information.
Craig: Now, like we said, something like Google,
Craig: you're going to get some Facebook posts
Craig: and blogs and things.
Craig: That's great.
Craig: They're all useful.
Craig: But AI is just crowdsourcing on such a
Craig: different level, and the telescope is
Craig: bringing back such a universe of
Craig: information that is then, like we say,
Craig: being individualized to your context,
Craig: that I feel, if I'm being a little bit
Craig: rogue at times in saying this, it would
Craig: be that you could actually say, is it
Craig: ethical to not use AI?
Craig: If AI can give you so much more
Craig: information about how to support your
Craig: child or the student compared to not
Craig: using it, it would be, I mean, you could
Craig: say, like a doctor in the health
Craig: profession, if they didn't go to
Craig: conferences and they didn't read research
Craig: journals and they just said, well, you
Craig: know, I think I know how to do this
Craig: surgery or to diagnose this patient, you'd
Craig: say, I don't think so.
Craig: you're not using the best and the latest
Craig: information that's out there. But if that doctor
Craig: uses AI in an educated, informed way to
Craig: suddenly crowdsource doctors' experiences
Craig: from all over
Craig: the world and the latest medical
Craig: breakthroughs and cross-cultural and
Craig: cross-topic references
Craig: that are coming through, you think that's
Craig: a really well-informed doctor. And I think the
Craig: same is true for parents and for teachers
Craig: not to put the pressure on everybody to
Craig: think you're a
Craig: bad parent if you don't use ai to consult
Craig: every single part of what you need to do
Craig: as a parent
Craig: or as as a teacher you're you're not a
Craig: good teacher if you don't use ai that's definitely
Craig: not true but i do think to myself what
Craig: are the ethics of using it and not using
Craig: it and what
Craig: might be missed if we're not at least
Craig: understanding what this space contains
Craig: and what could be gained
Craig: by just investigating investigating in in
Craig: a way that feels safe and sensible for
Craig: each of us and
Craig: not to listen to what the the crowd is
Craig: saying about ai or what the headlines are
Craig: saying but
Craig: actually sit down and have a little play
Craig: yourself and then i used to say to people
Craig: with the walk and
Craig: talk side, just try a little voice
Craig: conversation, say a few words, see how it
Craig: feels. And I think
Craig: people in their quieter moments or their
Craig: more reflective moments with this tech
Craig: can see a lot
Craig: of potential that maybe you don't always
Craig: hear about if you're just going off
Craig: headlines. I'm
Craig: cautiously optimistic in where it's all
Craig: going. It still inspires me every single
Craig: day while I'm
Craig: also completely you know savvy to the the
Craig: more difficult more challenging ethical
Craig: spaces that
Craig: it occupies i think both both things can
Craig: be true it can be both a potential
Craig: environmental challenge
Craig: economic workplace challenge social challenge
Craig: all the challenges are
Craig: absolutely going to be there
Craig: as a technology but that's not a reason
Craig: to not try to extract goodness from it
Craig: and the inclusive
Craig: benefits that could support our students
Craig: right now
Josh: definitely yeah and there's I
Josh: know so much
Josh: more that we could explore in this space
Josh: and so much more that's going to I guess
Josh: be uncovered
Josh: in the the weeks months and years from
Josh: here but I really appreciate your your
Josh: take on it and your
Josh: understanding of of the use of AR to this
Josh: point and the benefits that you've found
Josh: to this point
Josh: both in your own life and that of
Josh: educators and students that you've worked
Josh: with as well.
Josh: For people who would like to find out
Josh: more about the work that you're doing,
Josh: I know there's a lot on Universal Sandpit
Josh: in terms of some of your talks
Josh: and what you've written and other
Josh: recordings as well that you have.
Josh: There's obviously the tools on Universal
Josh: Sandpit as well.
Josh: What other spaces and places can we find
Josh: to keep updated
Josh: with what it is that you're doing, the
Josh: work you're doing,
Josh: and what you're exploring in this space?
Craig: Thank you, Josh. I definitely put the
Craig: best of what I do up on the Universal
Craig: Sandpit. I would also say that on
Craig: LinkedIn, I try to stay current on
Craig: LinkedIn. I post at least every week. And
Craig: I often put little experiments up there
Craig: that maybe I wouldn't put on the Sandpit
Craig: because they're just a one-off thing that
Craig: I've tried and played around with.
Craig: i find that it's it's interesting and i
Craig: mean you could have a whole conversation
Craig: around the
Craig: algorithms and social media but when i
Craig: put little experiments up on linkedin
Craig: that i think are really
Craig: fascinating with ai but they're very left
Craig: of center i get no engagement whatsoever
Craig: but the
Craig: moment that the moment that you mentioned
Craig: something about you know gee aren't children
Craig: you know doing poor with their reading i
Craig: wonder if it relates to ai you know you
Craig: get a thousand
Craig: people commenting so yeah i i just say
Craig: that that if if people are interested in
Craig: seeing some of the
Craig: more niche quirky little one-off things
Craig: that i'm doing with ai and education i do
Craig: put stuff up on
Craig: linkedin all the time so between the
Craig: universal cnp and linkedin you'll
Craig: definitely get a sense of what
Craig: i'm doing
Josh: yeah no that's fantastic and i
Josh: do encourage people to go and have a look at it
Josh: Because, like I say, it is a really great
Josh: space.
Josh: And I thank you, Craig, for creating it
Josh: and sharing it.
Josh: And, again, for sharing your thoughts and
Josh: ideas with us today.
Josh: I really, really appreciate you jumping
Josh: on the podcast.
Josh: And, yeah, let us know what other things
Josh: you find out and explore over the next
Josh: little while.
Josh: Because I'm very, very intrigued and keen
Josh: to keep up to date with what you keep
Josh: finding out.
Josh: So, thanks again. Appreciate it.
Craig: Well, thank you so much, Josh.
Craig: Thank you for having me on the podcast.
Craig: It's been wonderful to have this
Craig: conversation with you and look forward to
Craig: keeping in touch.
Josh: Big thank you to Craig for such an
Josh: interesting and thought-provoking
Josh: conversation.
Josh: I think that AI is one of those topics
Josh: where we probably don't have all the
Josh: answers yet
Josh: and perhaps that's exactly why it's worth
Josh: continuing to ask the questions.
Josh: There are so many ideas and tools that
Josh: Craig mentions throughout this
Josh: conversation
Josh: that are worth exploring for ourselves,
Josh: not necessarily because we know exactly
Josh: where they'll take us, but because they might
Josh: help us understand what is possible.
Josh: And I think the idea of using a double
Josh: empathy lens is particularly important as we navigate
Josh: this space, taking the time to understand
Josh: how other people might experience and use
Josh: technology differently from us.
Josh: If something from today's conversation
Josh: made you stop and think, we'd love to hear what
Josh: it was.
Josh: And if you enjoyed the episode, you can
Josh: follow or subscribe to the Parent Teacher Interview
Josh: Podcast wherever you listen to your
Josh: podcasts and find us on Instagram at
Josh: parentteacherinterviewpod.
Josh: And remember, there is no booking
Josh: required and we're looking forward to
Josh: seeing you along
Josh: at the next parent-teacher interview.